RG 018, Civil Service Commission
Connecticut State Library
Civil Service Commission records
1913-1921
Connecticut State Library
Connecticut. Civil Service Commission
18 cubic feet
The Civil Service Commission made rules, created classified job titles and tests, administered the tests and perepared eligibility lists, answered correspondence, and sought information about exempted or unclassified employees in State departments.
RG018
T000765
Historical Note
The Connecticut Civil Service Commission was created on June 6, 1913 (Connecticut General Assembly Public Acts, 1913, Chapter 232). With its inception, a dual form of state service was developed. Unclassified and classified categories were set up. Unclassified service was not subject to any of the provisions of the act, while applicants for classified service were required to take competitive examinations.
The Commission existed for a short time, as it was disbanded in April of 1921 (Connecticut General Assembly Public Acts, 1921, Chapter 126). It was not until 1937 that the Department of Personnel was created.
Scope and Content
Contains minutes, records of expenditure, reports, correspondence, lists of applicants and appointees, sample examinations, and files on hospital attendants and nurses.
Related Material
None
Index Terms
Organizations:
Connecticut. Civil Service Commission
Subjects:
Civil service -- Connecticut; Connecticut -- Officials and employees -- Appointment, qualificatons, tenure, etc; Civil service -- Examinations
Document Types:
Card files; Correspondence; Employees' manuals; Job applications; Minutes; Reports
Restrictions on Access
These records are stored at an off-site facility and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis.
See the policy.
Container List
- Records, 1913-1921
  - 1. Minutes of meetings, 1913-1920; 2 volumes (Box 1)
  - 2. Records of expenditure, 1913-1920 (Box 1)
  - 3. Reports and papers relating to the Civil Service Assembly, 1920 (Box 2)
    The Assembly of Civil Service Commissioners was held at Colorado Springs, Colorado, June 21-23, 1920.
    This group of papers also contains background material concerning the Connecticut Civil Service Commissions.
  - 4. Correspondence, 1914-1921
    - General Correspondence, 1914-1919
      - A-C (Box 3)
      - D-K (Box 4)
      - L-P (Box 5)
      - Q-Z (Box 6)
    - Correspondence with Departments and Institutions, 1914-1919
      - A-B (Box 7)
      - C-D (Box 8)
      - E-G (Box 9)
      - H-M (Box 10)
      - N-R (Box 11)
      - S-Z (Box 12)
    - General Correspondence, 1917-1919
      - A-M (Box 13)
      - M-Z (Box 14)
    - Correspondence with Departments and Institutions, 1917-1919
      - A-D (Box 15)
      - E-H (Box 16)
    - General Correspondence, 1919-1920
      - A-E (Box 17)
      - E-Z (Box 18)
    - General Correspondence, 1920-1921
      - A-L (Box 19)
      - M-Z (Box 20)
    - Correspondence with Departments and Institutions, 1919-1921
      - A-H (Box 21)
      - I-S (Box 22)
      - T-Z (Box 23)
  - 5. Subject file, 1914-1921
    Miscellaneous papers including applications for some state positions including nurses and attendants, permits for occasional employment, reports, and test statistics.
    Arranged by subject and there under chronologically.
    - A-E (Box 24)
    - F-P (Box 25)
    - R-Z (Box 26)
  - 6. Papers relating to appointments and certifications, 1914-1918 (Box 27)
    These papers consist primarily of form replies sent out to applicants.
    Arranged alphabetically
  - 7. Papers relating to out-of-state civil service systems, 1914-1916 (Box 28)
    Samples of manuals and applications used by other civil service systems. Also included in this group are miscellaneous correspondence and clippings.
    Very roughly arranged alphabetically by job class.
  - 8. Card record of applicants, 1914
    Alphabetical card file of applicants, recording the position applied for, and the rating the applicant received.
    - A-MI (Box 29)
    - MO-Z (Box 30)
  - 9. Reports of appointments, changes of salary, and terminations, 1914-1921
    Arranged alphabetically by department or institution.
    - A-M (Box 31)
    - N-W (Box 32)
  - 10. Miscellaneous forms, reports, and rules issued by the Civil Service Commission, 2 folders (Box 32)
    Unarranged
  - 11. Application register, 1913-1921 (Box Item 33)
    Information recorded includes the name and address, age and sex of the applicant, the date of application, position sought, test number, and chronological.
    The ledger is divided into two sections. The first section is a numerical listing of individuals who applied for state employment.
    The second half of the ledgers is a list of eligible candidates.
    Arranged alphabetically according to the position applied for.